<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the most honourable assembly of the Commons House in Parliament the humble petition of English marchants, trading into Spaine and France.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00292</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10413.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3058</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">29900281</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 29900281</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28118</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00292)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28118)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1861:82)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the most honourable assembly of the Commons House in Parliament the humble petition of English marchants, trading into Spaine and France.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Request for allowances on duties for spoiled wines and under guage casks, from the customs.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Includes also: "The copy of an order set downe at the Councell table for marchant strangers," dated, 15 Nov. 1612, and "The copy of a leter to Sir John Swinnerton, Knight, then L. Maior of London," dated 23 Nov. 1612.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Society of Antiquaries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Swinerton, John, --  Sir.</term>
               <term>Wine and wine making --  Law and legislation --  England.</term>
               <term>Wine adulteration.</term>
               <term>France --  Commerce --  England.</term>
               <term>Spain --  Comerce --  England.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Commerce --  France.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Commerce --  Spain.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  London (England) --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:28118:1"/>
            <head>¶To the moſt Honourable Aſſembly of the Commons Houſe in Parliament.</head>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>¶The Humble petition of Engliſh Marchants, trading into Spaine and France:</head>
               <opener>Humbly ſheweth,</opener>
               <p n="1">1 <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the Subſidie due to his Maieſty for one Tunne of French wine is 3. ſhillings being filled at the landing of the ſame.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The Engliſh Marchants of London, are now conſtrained to pay for euery Tunne that ſhalbe landed, be the Caske but halfe full, 3.
ſhillings Subſidie, 42. ſhillings impoſt, and 15. ſhillings for compoſition of purueyance: which charge of purueyance is payd onely in
London port, and began but lately: They alſo are compelled to pay 3. pounds vpon euery two pipes of Conneacke wines, which vſually
doe want 7. Ceſternes, and as much for euery 4. Hogsheads of High Countrey wines, when indeed 5. of them filled vp, doe not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
one Tunne of Aſsiſe. The Maligo and Canary Caske are alſo well knowne to be both vndergage.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The farme of ſweet wines (which ſometimes allowed 15.) doth now allow 12. in the 100 for leakadge, and all empty or refuſed Caske, euen to
marchant ſtrangers, as by an order of the 15. of Nouemb. 1612. appeares: which ſayd ſweet wines do pay no greater duties, and yet are knowne to be
much more durable, and of better worth. The vſe of former time hath beene to make ſome reſtitutution or allowance to the Marchant, for impoſt of
ſuch eager and decayed wines, as ſhould remaine on his hands vnſold at the yeeres end, which is now nothing at all regarded or conſidered of.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The wiſedome of Parliament anno 1. Rich. 3. did ordaine euery Tunne to containe 252. gallons, the butte or pipe 126. and the hogshead 63.
according to which meaſure, his Maiesties Officers ſhould receiue ſubſidie and duties, and for more certainty, euery port Towne hath a ſworne Officer, to
gadge all wines and oyles, before the Marchants can expoſe them to ſale, vpon paine of forfeiture, that the Subiects might be no more deceiued in gadge
of Caske as formerly they were.</p>
               <p n="5">5 The Farmers of the Cuſtomes, againſt all Law and equity, doe force the ſayd Merchants, to pay ſubſidie and other duties for full veſſels, though
often, vndergadge, vnſeene, or vnladen, when many of them want halfe their wine, and thereby receiue 4 pounds at leaſt, where 3 pound is not truly
due, or els will not ſuffer the marchant to land his goods, but ſeiſe them as forfeit for none cuſtome.</p>
               <p n="6">6 The Marchants being in great bonds to them for theſe duties, made in his Maiesties name, fearing to offend the Farmers, and to hazard their
credits and estates by ſudden extents, and willing to preuent the ſpoile and periſhing of their goods, are forced to yeeld, without any penalty or remedy,
againſt the Farmers ſo vnkindly and vnreaſonable oppreſsion.</p>
               <p>May it therefore pleaſe this most high Court, in tender regard of the premiſſes, to take ſuch courſe and order, for eaſe and reliefe of your Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliants
ſayd greeuance, as to your most graue wiſedomes, ſhall ſeeme meet and indifferent. And they as in duty ſhall daily pray for the
long health and happineſſe of ſo prudent, prouident, and compaſsionate an Aſſemblie.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Signed by</hi> William Bond, William Spight, William Palmer, Thomas Boothby, Thomas Frier, Richard Archdal, Henry Kinnerſlie, Iohn Dade,
Nicholas Smith, F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ancis Taylor, Edward Browne, Thomas Wetherall, Conway Manlye, George Benſon, Humfrey Slany, Thomas Bewley,
Marmaduke Rawdon, George Langham, Iohn Sherington, Iohn Worſop, Clement Harby, Richard Wiſeman, Francis Samborne, Tho. Walton,
Henry Lee, Thomas Hanſon, William Attwill, Henry Lee, Nathaniel Peacocke, Iohn Papril, Iohn Hall, William Bonham, Chriſtopher Barnes,
Thomas Eyre, Thomas Hampſon, Richard Barnabee, Francis Haddon, Richard Symmes, George Porter, William Gonnell, William Peacocke,
Thomas Slingesbye, Iohn Crabbe, Richard Trauis, Thomas Gilberd, Charles Atye, Roger Iackſon.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="order">
               <head>¶The copy of an Order ſet downe at the Councell Table for Marchant ſtrangers.</head>
               <p>WHereas vpon a petition heeretofore exhibited to this Bord by the Engliſh Marchants of London, trading Spaine, and other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
for ſweet wines, concerning an allowance to bee made vnto them for leakage, it was thought fit after diuers hearings of the
cauſe, to order, That there ſhould be an allowance made vnto them of 12 in the 100. by his Maieſties Farmers, of the impoſt of ſuch
ſweet wines as they brought into the port of London, as by the ſayd order more at large appeareth.</p>
               <p>And whereas the Marchant ſtrangers of the City of London, are in like manner, ſutors to the Bord, for an allowance to bee made
vnto them for leakeage, according as heeretofore hath alwayes beene vſed, being otherwiſe hardly able to driue a trade in that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity,
in regard of the double Subſidie, buttleridge, and other duties which they pay for thoſe wines, whereof the Engliſh, are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
freed and exempted; Their Lordſhips hauing conſidered aſwell of their petition, as the anſwer thereunto made by his Maieſties
Farmer, and being informed, That they haue alwaies had the ſame allowance heeretofore for leakage, as hath beene made vnto the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh:
and that in regard of the double ſubſedies and buttleridge, which they pay, the proportion of difference will ſtill hold to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage
of the natiue Marchants; It is therefore this day ordered, That his Maieſties Farmer of the impoſt of ſweet wines, ſhall make
the like allowance of 12 in the 100 of the old impoſt and ſubſidie onely, for leakage of ſuch wines contayned in his Leaſe, as ſhall bee
brought into this kingdome by the ſayd Marchant ſtrangers, in ſuch manner and forme as is made vnto the Engliſh marchants: And it
is likewiſe ordered, That ſuch Caske as is out end for end, or left for fraught, ſhalbe likewiſe allowed vnto them. Prouided neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe,
That for ſuch ſweet wines as are brought into this Realme by the ſayd merchants, either out of France, or the Low Countreyes,
allowance is to be made of 5 in the 100 as in former times hath beene vſed. And it is alſo ordered for the auoyding of any further
difference in this behalfe, That the ſayd Marchants do fill no wines on boord after they come into this Realme. Sunday the 15. of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uember,
1612.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>Lord Archbiſhop of Canterbury.</item>
                        <item>Lord Chancellour.</item>
                        <item>Duke of Lennox.</item>
                        <item>Lord Admirall.</item>
                        <item>Lord Chamberlaine.</item>
                        <item>Earle of Worceſter.</item>
                        <item>Earle of Pembroke.</item>
                        <item>Lord Priuie Seale.</item>
                        <item>Lord Wootton.</item>
                        <item>Lord Stanhop.</item>
                        <item>Lord Knolles.</item>
                        <item>Sir Iohn Harbert.</item>
                        <item>Sir Iulius Ceſar.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>¶The copy of a Letter to Sir Iohn Swinnerton Knight, then L. Maior of London.</head>
               <p>WEe did not expect to haue found ſuch difficulty in your Lordſhip, in ſubmitting your ſelfe to the Order lately made on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe
of Marchant ſtrangers, concerning the leakage of ſweet wines, being done vpon ſo iuſt grounds, and agreeable to the vſage
of former times, and that with as much indifferency and reſpect to your Lo. as the cauſe would beare: but foraſmuch as the ſayd
Marchants are much damnified in ſuch wines as are now ready to be diſcharged in that port of London, and cannot bee landed but by
order from your Lordſhip, We doe heereby require you for the auoyding of any further preiudice therein, to ſigne ſuch warrants as
ſhalbe meet for the landing of the ſayd wines, vpon ſecurity giuen by them for payment of ſuch dueties as are due vpon the ſame, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
we haue thought meet likewiſe to mooue your Lordſhip, not to ſtand too ſtrictly vpon ſecurity they ſhall offer, in reſpect they may be
ſtrangers, otherwiſe knowne to bee ſufficient for the ſame. And ſo expecting due performance heereof, without further trouble to this
Bord, we bid you &amp;c. <date>Sunday the 23. of Nouember. 1612.</date>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>Lord priuie Seale.</item>
                        <item>Lord Chamberlaine.</item>
                        <item>Earle of Worceſter.</item>
                        <item>Lord Zouch.</item>
                        <item>Lord Wootton.</item>
                        <item>Sir Iulius Ceſar.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
